<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons One, the curse and crime of Meroz. Preached at the assises at Exon. The other, a sermon of patience. At St Maries in Oxford. By Edward Gee, Doctor in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie. Published since his death, by his two brethren, Iohn Gee and George Gee, ministers of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Gee, Edward, 1565-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103012</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838771</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1237:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons One, the curse and crime of Meroz. Preached at the assises at Exon. The other, a sermon of patience. At St Maries in Oxford. By Edward Gee, Doctor in Diuinitie, and chaplaine to his Maiestie. Published since his death, by his two brethren, Iohn Gee and George Gee, ministers of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Gee, Edward, 1565-1618.</author>
                  <author>Gee, John, d. 1631.</author>
                  <author>Gee, George, b. 1574 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W[illiam] S[tansby] for Nathaniel Butter, and are to be sold at his shop neere S. Austins-gate, at the signe of the Pyde Bull,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Iohn Gee and George Gee," are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"A sermon of patience" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3159:1"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS.</p>
            <p>ONE, The Curſe and Crime of <hi>Meroz. Preached at the Aſsiſes at Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE other, A Sermon of <hi>Patience, At</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Maries <hi>in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY EDWARD GEE, Doctor in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to his MAIESTIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed ſince his death, by his</hi> two brethren, IOHN GEE and GEORGE GEE, Miniſters of Gods Word.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi>-gate, at the ſigne of the Pyde Bull. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3159:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3159:2"/>
            <head>A Premonition to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O yeeld any reaſons for the publiſhing theſe Sermons (conſidering the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of the Author, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Argument) were to call into queſtion the valew of an Offering caſt into the treaſurie of Gods Church. If <hi>TERTVLLIAN,</hi> an ancient and learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (when the Light of the Goſpel ſhined neerer the times of the primitiue puritie) confeſſed that hee did adore the fulneſſe of the Scriptures: Haue wee leſſe cauſe, in theſe dayes (indeed not of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but of contention and libertie) to reſpect the ſincere Expoſitors of the Myſteries of GOD? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when euerie man is almoſt become an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretor to himſelfe. But for as much as they who are the Publiſhers of theſe exerciſes, can beſt giue reſolution for their publication, (how euer extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie occaſions vnexpectedly withcal'd them for the preſent;) yet, where a man in his life time ſo knowne, and ſo deſeruing to be knowne for ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of conucrſation, generalitie of learning, graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of iudgement, and ſoundneſſe of Doctrine (as
<pb facs="tcp:3159:3"/>the Author was) hath left any monument of his ſtudies; there it cannot bee but an iniurie to his memorie, and a kindt of defrauding the Store-houſe of Religion, to conceale that for any priuate vſe, which concernes a publique benefit. A Teacher, after his death, is beſt commended, by the remaining fruits of his labours; thoſe parcell-reliques of this worthie man, being then read, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtood, and applyed, cannot but both informe the charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtian Reader, and confirme him.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3159:3"/>
                  <head>THE CVRSE AND CRIME OF <hi>MEROZ.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>IVDG. 5. VERS. 23.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Curſe yee <hi>Meroz,</hi> (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe continually the Inhabitants thereof; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they came not to helpe the Lord, to helpe the Lord againſt the mightie.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is the firſt care of a good Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (right Honourable, right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, and welbeloued) to purge and rid his Garden-plot of all noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearbes, and peſtilent weedes: So is it the chiefeſt worke of a wiſe Gouernour to remoue all naughtie and incurable perſons from a Citie and Common-weale. The which wee need not to proue by the authorities of <hi>Solon, Lycurg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3159:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>or other Heatheniſh Law-giuers, but euen by the preſcript of the wiſdome of God, the well and fountaine of perfect policie. For when the Lord had brought his vine out of Aegypt, and had giuen to the people of Iſrael the land of Canaan, he firſt and principally charged them that they ſhould vtterly root out the idolatrous Cananites, that they ſhould make no league of friendſhip with them, but without all compaſſion, ſmite and deſtroy them <hi>from the face of the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.2.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. And this commandement they kept religiouſly, both vnder the flouriſhing gouernment of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and of the Elders alſo which ſucceeded him. But after, when they had taken roote in the fruitfull land, and plentie had begotten eaſe, and eaſe had bred ſecuritie, and ſecuritie had brought forth forgetfulneſſe of God, and forgetfulneſſe of God had cauſed them to make an impious truce with the curſed Cananites,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.28.</note> whom for a little tribute they ſuffered to liue quietly in the middeſt of their land: the Lord did therefore bring vpon them many calamities, and gaue them vp often to bee ſubdued and tyrannouſly oppreſſed by thoſe prophane Nations. And yet behold the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercie, did in the middeſt of his furie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mercie. For in their greateſt oppreſſions, whenſoeuer they truely repented and turned vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.16.</note> he raiſed them vp Iudges, that is to ſay, rare and extraordinarie Champions, men of vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and heroicall ſpirits, which by ſtrong hand deliuered them from their oppreſſours. Witneſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3159:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>this one example for all in the fourth Chapter of this Booke, wherein it is hard to ſay, whether the oppreſſion was more grieuous, or the deliuerance more famous. For the Lord had ſold his people into the hands of <hi>Iabin</hi> King of Canaan, whoſe munitions, euen nine hundreth chariots of yron, ſeemed vnreſiſtable; his ſouldiers innumerable, his Captaine <hi>Siſera</hi> inuincible, who by continuall excurſions had ouer-runne the whole land for the ſpace of twentie yeares. And yet when they called vpon God in their diſtreſſe, hee raiſed vp <hi>Debora</hi> the Propheteſſe, who perſwaded <hi>Barac</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Abinoam,</hi> to take vnto him tenne thouſand ſouldiers of the Tribes of <hi>Zebulon</hi> and <hi>Nepthalye,</hi> and with that handfull of men, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter that huge Hoſte of the Cananites in a pitched field neere vnto the brooke Kiſhon; whoſe armie was three hundred thouſand men and more, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> writeth. In which battaile <hi>Iabin</hi> was for euer vanquiſhed, the Cananites diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited, their chariots diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, &amp; their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Siſera</hi> moſt diſhonourably nayled vnto the ground with a pinne of a Tent ſtrucken through the temples of his head by the hands of <hi>Iael,</hi> the wife of <hi>Heber.</hi> And vpon that glorious victorie, <hi>Barac</hi> and <hi>Debora</hi> did ſing this ſweete ſong of thankeſgiuing vnto God, in the fift Chapter of this Booke.</p>
                  <p>In which moſt excellent &amp; triumphant Hymne, as the Authors name is <hi>Debora,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deb. ſignif.</note> which ſignifies a <hi>Bee,</hi> ſo doth ſhe bring not onely the ſweet hony
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3159:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of praiſe and thanks-giuing for that glorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, but alſo a ſharpe ſting of reproofe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe pierceth thoſe Tribes and men that came not to helpe them in that great extremitie. But of all the Iſraelites that abſented themſelues, there were none ſo faultie as the men of <hi>Meroz,</hi> who dwelling neere vnto Mount Thabor where the field was foughten, and beeing called vpon to come, did notwithſtanding hide their heads in the day of battaile. And therefore this holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſe doth thunder as it were from heauen a ſpeciall malediction againſt them, ſaying, <hi>Curſe yee</hi> Meroz, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which words are nothing elſe but a direfull doome of <hi>Debora</hi> againſt the mercileſſe <hi>Merozites;</hi> wherein, for breuities ſake, I will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue but</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Points.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Curſe of</hi> Meroz; and what it was.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Crime of</hi> Meroz; and how great it was.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Concerning the former,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Part.</note> the meaning is, that an Angel of God, to wit, either <hi>Barac,</hi> as the Chaldee paraphraſe doth render it, or ſome other Prophet inſpired from aboue, as I expound it, did commaund both the Iudges and the people to pray for the ruine and vtter deſtruction of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz,</hi> and of all that dwelt therein.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> Now if any man aske whether the command of this Angel be not contrarie to the command of that great Angel of the Couenant, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3159:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>who bids vs in the Goſpel to <hi>bleſſe them that curſe vs, and pray for them that perſecute vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44.</note> whereunto heauens great trumpet S. <hi>Paul</hi> accordeth, ſaying,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſe, and curſe not:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> there is no repugnancie in theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. For as the Word of God forbiddeth all intemperate heat and deſire of reuenge in our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate wrongs, and ſo all manner of curſings of our priuate enemies; ſo doth it require vs to hate the enemies of God, with a perfect hatred, and to curſe them vnto the death, if we be certified from heauen that they be incorrigible, and that the Lord hath appointed them vnto ſlaughter. Hence the holy Prophets of God, who being rauiſhed in the Spirit, were carryed vp into heauen vpon the wings of prayer and prophecie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.</note> as <hi>Elias</hi> in a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie chariot, and did behold in the criſtall glaſſe of Gods ſecret counſaile, who were the incurable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of God, deſtined vnto deſtruction, could not chuſe but with their hearts wiſh, and with their tongues expreſſe their longing deſire to haue the iudgements of God put in execution. Hence proceeded the curſes of <hi>Eliſaeus,</hi> of <hi>Elias,</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> of other holy men of God, who being endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Spirit of diſcerning, and inflamed with a pure zeale of Gods glorie, did pray for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of them, who were alreadie by the Iudge of the whole world appointed vnto death. And therefore Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith of ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall imprecations,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> that they were rather <hi>Verba praedicentium, quàm vota imprecantium,</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3159:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>words of prediction, than wiſhes of malediction. But as for vs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 7.14.</note> who <hi>are neither Prophets nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſonnes,</hi> nor haue any extraordinarie gift of Gods Spirit, we may not abſolutely wiſh for the deſtruction of any, leſt our Sauiour ſay vnto vs as he did vnto his Diſciples, wiſhing for fire from heauen vpon their enemies,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 9.55.</note> 
                     <hi>You know not of what Spirit you are.</hi> Yet may we conditionally curſe the enemies of God and his Church, if ſo be the Kingdome of Chriſt cannot be eſtabliſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their deſtruction. Wherein notwithſtanding we muſt beware that we ſuffer the holy Ghoſt to ſit as pilot in our hearts, and to rule the rudder of our tongues, leſt by any mixture of humane infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, we doe adulterate the Word of God. For as a little inke which is powred into a Spring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all the water blacke that iſſueth from it, and a little <hi>Coloquintida</hi> ſpoyled all the Pottage of the Prophets,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 4.</note> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4. and one dead Flie corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a whole pot of oyntment: euen ſo doth a little malice make the iudgements of God which thou pronounceſt, both vnprofitable vnto thy brethren, and damnable vnto thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>So that the Doctrine is this, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> &amp; the vſe is good. Where the Lord of Heauen doth firſt curſe, there <hi>Debbora</hi> and <hi>Barac,</hi> the Miniſter and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, muſt both curſe; the one with the Word, the other with the Sword; the one by exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the other by execution; the one fore-telling, the other inflicting the iudgements of God vpon notorious offenders without affection or partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3159:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> Strange it is that the Lord commanded theſe Iudges of Iſrael to ſtrike the <hi>Merozites,</hi> their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, with ſuch a <hi>Maranatha</hi> in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; but it is a notable precedent to teach all Magiſtrates, that when the Lords will is reuealed vnto them, either by his Word, or by his Spirit, or by the Edicts of wholſome Lawes, that any haynous offendours are appointed vnto death, their eyes muſt not then pittie them, nor their hearts muſt haue compaſſion on them, but with all wholſome ſeueritie they muſt proſecute them vnto their end. When the people of Iſrael had committed Idolatrie with the Golden Calfe, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> called the Leuites, and bade euerie one put his Sword by his ſide, and <hi>ſlay euerie man his brother,</hi> and euery man his companion, and euery man his neighbour, that ſo they might conſecrate their hands vnto the Lord, and receiue a bleſſing; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Leuites ſlew three thouſand men, or thereabouts. The which zeale of the Leuites in reuenging Gods glorie, did ſo pleaſe the Lord, that for it the curſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> againſt <hi>Leui</hi> was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a bleſſing, as appeareth by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Swan-like Song, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. And of <hi>Leui</hi> he ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 33:8, 93.</note> 
                     <hi>Let thy Vrim and thy Thummim be with thy holy one who ſaid of his father and mother, I haue not ſeene them, neither knew he his brethren or his owne children,</hi> meaning that he preferred Gods glorie before naturall affection. The which example would to God it were written in the hearts of all Iudges. But yet let them ſtill remember to curſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3159:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>no otherwhere, but there where God himſelfe hath curſed.</p>
                  <p>The falſe Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> could ſay,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.8.</note> 
                     <hi>How ſhall I curſe where the Lord hath not curſed, or how ſhould I detest where the Lord hath not detested?</hi> And how farre be wee then from this rule, who are ſo tender of our owne reputation, that if we be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched neuer ſo little with the ſcourge of the toung, we are like that cloyſter in Thebes which <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Plutarch. Moral.</note> which for euery word that was ſpoken in it would giue an eccho of ſeuen ſounds; euen ſo doe we returne ſeuen curſes for one into his boſome that reuileth vs: But when the name of God is blaſphemed, his honour defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, his precepts neglected, we are <hi>muti vt piſces,</hi> or if we open our mouthes,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>55.</hi>
                     </note> our <hi>words are ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Oyle,</hi> and our faces are as cheerefull as if we had found a treaſure.</p>
                  <p>Well; the Spirit of God doth curſe <hi>Meroz,</hi> and what was this curſe? Surely it was no <hi>verbal malediction,</hi> but a <hi>reall effuſion</hi> of the wrath of God vpon the Inhabitants of that towne. For though <hi>a cauſeleſſe curſe</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.) <hi>be like vnto a Swallow that flyeth from the hand,</hi> and lighteth not there whither ſhe was ſent; yet are the curſes of God, and his Prophets, like vnto <hi>Ionathans</hi> bow and <hi>Sauls</hi> ſword,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.</note> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne not emptie from the bloud of the ſlaine and the fat of the mightie, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. Witneſſe <hi>Eliſha,</hi> who had no ſooner curſed the <hi>children of Bethel,</hi> but they were by and by <hi>deuoured by two Beares</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3159:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of the deſert, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 2. Witneſſe <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.</note> who had no ſooner curſed <hi>Ananias</hi> and and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> but they by and by fell downe dead at th'apoſtles feete, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. And our Sauiour had no ſooner curſed the Figge-tree,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>5.</hi> Mark. <hi>112</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 11. but it by and by withers vnto the ground. And ſurely the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiſme which <hi>Debbora</hi> vſeth in my text, iterating the curſe againe and againe, doth manifeſtly ſhew that the curſe of <hi>Meroz</hi> was no common or eaſie imprecation,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</note> but <hi>anathema maranatha</hi> in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree; it was a vehement and effectuall curſe which lighted not onely vpon their goods, but vpon their perſons alſo; neither vpon their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but vpon their ſoules alſo; a curſe which (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>couered them like a garment,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.18.19.</note> 
                     <hi>gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them like a girdle, and entred euen as water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their bowels, and as oyle into their bones.</hi> For how fearefull a thing was it to be curſed by the Lord, whoſe wordes are as <hi>two-edged ſwords,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> whoſe voice is as <hi>the voice of thunder:</hi> and whoſe breath is as <hi>a Riuer of Brimſtone which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto the bottome of hell?</hi> Surely if the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſaid truely, that the <hi>Mothers curſe roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out the foundations of the childrens houſes:</hi> then how much more powerfull is the curſe of our heauenly Father, whoſe irefull countenance maketh the earth to tremble, the heauens to bow,<note place="margin">Nahum. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> the ſeas to be dried vp, the rockes to rent, and the mountaines to melt away with feare? And what then ſhall we thinke, but that the houſes of the <hi>Merozites,</hi> which they hoped by their policie to continue, were now blaſted by the breath of Gods
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3159:8"/>mouth, and for euer ruinated by his curſe? Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of God, ſo is it as horrible alſo to be curſed by the mouth of God.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I ſpeake of this, that they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted execrable of the people of God, that they were cut off from the Common-wealth of Iſrael, that they were as Iericho and other Cities of the Cananites, deuoted vnto deſtruction? So that as the Citie of Rome when they condemned <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> of treaſon,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> vſed this Preface; <hi>Manlius eras mihi cum praecipites agebas Senones; poſt quam mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari coepiſti, factus es vnus ex Senonibus:</hi> When thou threweſt downe the Galls from the Capitol, then waſt thou to me <hi>Manlius,</hi> that is, faithfull and deare; but ſithence thou art now changed, I eſteeme thee no better then one of the Galls: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo ſaid Iſrael vnto the <hi>Merozites;</hi> As long as you ioyned with vs againſt <hi>Canaan,</hi> we counted you our brethren, but now you are changed and eſtranged from vs, you are no better then the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Cananites.</hi> Surely this was verie grieuous to be anathematized by the people of God, but it was not all; for no doubt the conſideration of their owne ſinne did ſo lancinate and torment their guiltie conſciences, that they had a taſte and prelibation of thoſe helliſh torments, the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wherof they did after endure, if they did not repent.</p>
                  <p>This was the heauie weight of the curſe of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roz,</hi> whoſe puniſhment who ſo liſteth to eſcape,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3159:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>let him eſchew their foule and vgly ſinne, which is the ſecond part I promiſed to declare.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Now peraduenture you will marueile why ſo heauie a iudgement was pronounced againſt a ſinne that may ſeeme light,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Part.</note> becauſe it was but the <hi>omiſsion</hi> of a dutie they ſhould haue done.</p>
                  <p>But if you take the ballance of the Lords San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, and put thereinto the ſinne of <hi>Meroz,</hi> you ſhall find it would weigh down heauen and earth, and neuer be counterpoiſed till it came to the bottome of hell. It was not a ſingle ſinne, as a man would thinke at the firſt ſight, but a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſinne, made and compounded of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the words of my Text doe make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. For behold, <hi>they came not,</hi> and that was <hi>ſlothfulneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>to helpe,</hi> and that was <hi>vnmercifulneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>the Lord;</hi> that <hi>wickedneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>againſt the mightie,</hi> and that was <hi>feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> if they had dwelled farre off, their lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe might haue beene excuſed; if they had not beene called, their ſinne had been ſomewhat ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened; if they had come, though ſtarting backe, as the Ephraimites did in the day of battaile, their offence had beene much leſſened. But alaſſe! they were neere, and were ſolemnely called, and yet neuer came out of the doores to helpe their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
                  <p>O ſenſeleſſe and dul-hearted <hi>Merozites,</hi> whom
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3159:9"/>neither the warlicke trumpets of battell, nor the whirling noyſe of ſo many yron Chariots, nor the beating of ſo many horſes hoofes, nor the skrikes and outcries of ſuch a multitude of men, could once awake from the ſlumber of ſinfull ſecuritie. Doubtleſſe theſe <hi>Merozites</hi> were giuen to their eaſe, and therefore vnwilling they were to trouble themſelues with that hote bickering; but they ſhould haue conſidered that of <hi>Salomon;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.32.</note> 
                     <hi>Eaſe ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the fooliſh, and the proſperitie of fooles deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What <hi>vnmercifulneſſe</hi> was it in them to hide themſelues from their owne fleſh, that is, their brethren, both by nature and by religion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in that great danger when their liues lay at ſtake, their kingdome like to be vſurped, and themſelues readie to be deuoured of their gaſtly and bloudie enemies?<note place="margin">Pro. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>The mercies of the wicked are meere cruelties,</hi> and ſuch indeed was the mercie of theſe men of <hi>Meroz,</hi> without loue, without pittie, without the bowells of compaſſion toward their brethren.</p>
                  <p>Oh, but peraduenture they thought it skilled not much, whether they went into the field or no, becauſe if God meant to giue them victorie, hee would then ſurely doe it without their aſſiſtance. As though euery man were not bound by the rule of charitie, as much as in him lies, to helpe Gods cauſe, and to defend the weake from the oppreſſion of the mightie. A notable inſtance whereof we haue in the booke of <hi>Hester.</hi> For
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3159:9"/>when as <hi>Purim</hi> was gone out againſt the Iewes,<note place="margin">Heſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> and <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> had made a bloudie decree to root all that Nation vtterly out of his land, noble <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dechay</hi> perſwaded <hi>Heſter,</hi> to interpoſe her ſelfe a mediatrix vnto the King for the ſafetie of her Country-men the Iewes; who when ſhe feared and caſt many doubts, <hi>Mordechay</hi> did ſharpely reply, That if ſhe neglected to relieue the Church and children of God, deliuerance ſhould ſurely come by ſome other meanes, but ſhe and her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe ſhould ſurely periſh: Euen ſo ſhould the <hi>Merozites</hi> haue thought, That howbeit the Lord would by his ſtrong hand, and ſtretched out arme haue deliuered his people, yet ſhould not the <hi>vnmercifulneſſe</hi> of <hi>Meroz,</hi> haue eſcaped ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, whoſe hard and flintie hearts either knew not their brethrens miſerie; or if they knew it, they conſidered it not; or if they conſidered, they pittied it not; or if they pittied, they relieued it not; but as much as in them lay, ſuffered them to be deuoured of their oppreſſours.</p>
                  <p>Doubtleſſe it was ſauage and barbarous <hi>imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> ſo to forſake the cauſe of their deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But what doe I ſpeake of <hi>immanitie?</hi> it was no leſſe than <hi>wicked impietie,</hi> not onely becauſe they were cruell againſt the Lord in that they helped not his children, who are as deare to him as the apple of his eye; but alſo becauſe it was the Lords quarrell in a ſpeciall regard.</p>
                  <p>The Iſraelites and the Cananites did now fight, <hi>non vter imperaret, ſed vter eſſet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tul.</note> as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3159:10"/>of the Romans and Carthaginians; not ſo much whether of them ſhould beare ſway, as whether of them ſhould ſolely remaine in the land. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it onely the queſtion, whether of the two Nations ſhould be left aliue, but alſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, whether the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> or the Idols of the <hi>Cananites</hi> ſhould be worſhipped. They did not ſo much ſtriue for the bounds and territories of the earth, as for the priuiledges and heſts of heauen.</p>
                  <p>For it was now the queſtion, whether IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH ſhould ſit ſtill betweene the Cherubines, and fill the Tabernacle with his glorious preſence; or whether he ſhould goe from Iſrael, and in ſtead thereof, <hi>Dagon, Moloch, Chemoſh,</hi> and other ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of the Heathen ſhould be adored. Seeing then that the worſhip of God was in ſo great hazard, in reſpect wherof we ſhould eſteeme all worldy things but as droſſe and dung, how wicked and irreligious were the <hi>Merozites,</hi> who were ſo calme and ſilent in the Lords quarrell?</p>
                  <p>Oh! <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> but peraduenture they feared the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of King <hi>Iabin;</hi> they feared his horſes, his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, his ſouldiers, and his great power: they doubted the great armie of the Cananites would deuoure the Iſraelites, euen as the Oxe licketh vp the graſſe?</p>
                  <p>And what was that but a carnall diffidence, and a foule diſtruſt of Gods mercie? Why did they not remember the wonders which the Lord had done for their Fore-fathers in the land of Aegypt?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3159:10"/>Had they forgotten the redde ſea, the pillar of cloud, and the <hi>Manna</hi> in the deſert? Or if theſe things were too ancient, could they not call to mind, how they were deliuered of late from the Cananites by <hi>Ehud</hi> a man lame of his right hand,<note place="margin">Judg. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> who ſlew <hi>Eglon</hi> King of Moab: and by <hi>Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> from the Philiſtines, who ſlew fiue hundred of them with an Oxe goade? Euen ſo it pleaſed God by weak inſtruments to bring mightie things to paſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> that the whole honour might redound vnto his name, and that his people might wholly rely vpon his ſauing health.</p>
                  <p>And why then ſhould <hi>Meroz</hi> feare that the Lords arme was ſhortened that hee could not helpe, or his will changed that he would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue? But if they had beene aſſured that they ſhould haue loſt the field, and all beene put to the edge of the ſword, they ſhould not haue feared them that could haue <hi>killed the bodies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>but rather him that could throw both bodie and ſoule into hell fire.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Merozites</hi> were verie fooliſh for feare of the anger of men, to fall into the curſe of God. Not vnlike <hi>Ionas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ionas <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> who flying vnto Tharſis for feare of Nineueh, fell into the Sea, and the belly of the Whale. So ſure it is that he who is not willing to be a Martyr of God, ſhall nilling be made a Martyr of the Deuil; and he that will not <hi>ſuffer for a good cauſe vnto ſaluation;</hi> ſhall be ſure to ſuffer for a bad cauſe <hi>vnto condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this Doctrine (right reuerend Auditors)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3159:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>goeth neere euerie one of vs, both Miniſters of the Word, and Miniſters of Iuſtice. For we can be content <hi>to helpe the Lord,</hi> that is, to reproue and puniſh ſinne in the inferiour and baſer ſort of the people; but when we ſhould <hi>helpe the Lord against the mightie Anachims,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> and great men of the World, woe is me to tell! our hearts doe faint, our courage is abated, and our minds are vtterly danted; not vnlike them of whom <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">Ier. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>They bend their tongues as their Bowes for lies, but they haue no courage for the truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O noble <hi>Caleb,</hi> as was thy name, ſo was thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">Caleb ſignif.</note> For <hi>Caleb</hi> ſignifies, <hi>as it were an heart,</hi> and thou waſt heartie and couragious in the Lords cauſe. Thou choſeſt <hi>Hebron</hi> to expell the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chims</hi> the mightie Gyants from the citie: but alas we loſe not <hi>Hebron</hi> but <hi>Heauen</hi> for feare of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let vs returne vnto the <hi>Merozites,</hi> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture thought themſelues innocent, becauſe they tooke no part againſt Iſrael, nor yet ioyned with the King of Canaan. Wherein they were much deceiued. For as the Lord abhorreth all <hi>Vterques,</hi> ſuch as were they that <hi>halted betwixt God and Baal,</hi> and they that ſpake both of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Aſhdod and Canaan, and they that were <hi>neither hote nor colde, but lukewarme:</hi> euen ſo can the Lord as little endure thoſe politique Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which were neither with him nor againſt him.</p>
                  <p>I reade in <hi>Liuie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Liuius lib. Hiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> that when the Romans and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3159:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Albans were at warres together, a noble man cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> doubting whether would get the vpper hand, ioyned with neither armie, but houered on a hil with his forces betwixt both, till he ſaw whither the victorie did incline; with which trecherie, the Romans (being conquerors) were ſo offended, that they tore him in pieces with wilde Horſes: A iuſt puniſhment for one that would ſtand neutrall when his Countrie was like to be ouerthrowne; which as they knew by the Law of Nature, ſo doe we know by the Word of God, that in matters of Religion and execution of Iuſtice, neutralitie is alwaies execrable. Our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour hath giuen vs the rule:<note place="margin">Luc. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>He that is not with me, he is against me, and he that gathereth not with mee, ſcattereth abroad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if any man thinke, that though the ſinne of <hi>Meroz</hi> was very great, yet it was the leſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as they did not <hi>helpe,</hi> ſo they did not <hi>hurt</hi> the people of God; let him remember, that as firmely as we are bound to <hi>eſchew euill,</hi> ſo firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are we bound to <hi>doe good</hi> when time and opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie doth require. And ſo I will conclude the ſinne of <hi>Meroz</hi> with this one corollarie: That it is not ſufficient for you (right reuerend brethren) to be <hi>harmeleſſe and innocent men,</hi> and to doe no iniurie vnto others, but you muſt alſo <hi>ſuccour and relieue your brethren in their good cauſes,</hi> by your <hi>ſubstance,</hi> by your <hi>counſaile,</hi> and by your <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> which are the golden Talents whereof you muſt giue an account at the latter day.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3159:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> For when the Thrones ſhall be ſet in heauen,<note place="margin">Reuci. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> and the Bookes opened, and the Sonne of man ſhall hold the great aſſiſes of the world, to giue to <hi>euerie man according to his workes;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> it ſhall not then ſo much be inquired, what ſinnes thou haſt <hi>committed,</hi> as what dueties thou haſt <hi>omitted;</hi> what euill thou haſt <hi>done,</hi> as what good thou haſt left <hi>vndone;</hi> what acts of <hi>crueltie</hi> thou haſt <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> as what acts of <hi>charitie</hi> thou haſt <hi>neglected.</hi> It ſhall then be examined, whether thou <hi>feddest Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> when <hi>thou ſaweſt him hungrie,</hi> and <hi>cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedſt Chriſt, when thou ſaweſt him naked,</hi> and <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitedst Chriſt, when thou ſaweſt him impriſoned,</hi> and in a word, whether thou deliueredſt Chriſt when thou <hi>ſaweſt him oppreſſed.</hi> Then ſhall <hi>mercie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce against iudgement,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. <hi>2.13.</hi>
                     </note> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, and <hi>iudgement ſhall be mercileſſe vnto them that ſhew no mercie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>HItherto haue I lanched forth (right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) ſtraight forward into the depth of my Text;<note place="margin">Application generall to the preſent occaſion.</note> and now, fearing to be carried too far with the pleaſant blaſt of your attention, I will ſtrike ſayles, and ſpeedily returne vnto the ſhore.</p>
                  <p>For perhaps ſome man will pull mee by the ſleeue, and ſay, <hi>Quid Marticum Legibus?</hi> What hath a Text of Warres to doe with the affaire of Peace? What is <hi>Canaan</hi> vnto <hi>England?</hi> What is <hi>Meroz</hi> vnto <hi>Deuon?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Preached in Deuonſhire.</note> Or what is the battle of the Cananites vnto this ſetled iudgement which is now to begin?</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3159:12"/>
                  <p> Yes ſurely, if we looke about vs, we ſhall finde that the curſed Cananites doe euerie where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and ſo much the more dangerouſly fight againſt vs, becauſe they come not into a pitched field, as they did of old, but lie ſecretly in ambuſh to hurt the innocent.</p>
                  <p>And what are theſe great Aſſiſes which you haue in hand, but as it were a great battaile, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both Iudges and Iuſtices, and Counſailors, and Iurors, and euerie one in his ranke muſt fight, not with the ſharpeneſſe of weapons, but with the ſeueritie of the Lawes, againſt the <hi>Romiſh Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> the bloudie <hi>Pereſites,</hi> and the wicked <hi>Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi> which ſeeke to diſturbe the peace of our Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? Behold our two gracious Princes, firſt <hi>Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bora</hi> and now <hi>Barac,</hi> haue for many yeares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued this battle of Iuſtice, to the comfort of the godly, to the confuſion of the wicked, to the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and aſtoniſhment of the whole World. It may truely be ſaid, that in the daies of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors the high waies were vnoccupied, and trauellors walked through by waies, by reaſon of the multitude of theeues and robbers; and that which was moſt horrible, the <hi>Romiſh Iabin</hi> did keepe the ſoules and conſciences of men in a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſlauery, vntill our late <hi>Debbora</hi> roſe vp a mother in Iſrael, who brake the Cananitiſh yoke, and brought in the halcionian dayes of peace, which by the goodneſſe of God, and our bleſſed <hi>Barac,</hi> we doe ſtill enioy. And yet I know not how it commeth to paſſe, that many reliques of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3159:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Cananites, that is to ſay, idolatrous Papiſts and cruell robbers, and bloudie oppreſſors of the poore, and many other enormous offendors doe yet remaine in the midſt of our land. And what is the cauſe of this confuſion? Surely one of the greateſt cauſes of our miſerie is this, that ſuch as ought to come to theſe Aſſiſes, and to fight the Lords battles againſt ſinne and ſuperſtition, are negligent in comming <hi>to helpe the Lord</hi> in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>For to ſpeake nothing of them that come not at all, whereof ſome with <hi>Reuben</hi> abide among the Sheepe-folds to heare the bleating of their flockes, they are <hi>couetous;</hi> ſome with <hi>Gilead</hi> tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> in the greene fields and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of their delights, they are <hi>voluptuous;</hi> ſome with <hi>Dan</hi> remaine in ſhips, and are beyond the Seas, in heart doting vpon their Romiſh I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, they are <hi>ſuperſtitious;</hi> ſome with <hi>Meroz,</hi> hide themſelues at home in the dearne cells of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, and they are <hi>timerous;</hi> How few, I ſay, of thoſe that doe come to this iudiciarie field, doe come as they ought, with care and conſcience to <hi>helpe the Lord againſt the mightie?</hi> Nay moſt part of them (woe is me to tell!) come not to <hi>helpe,</hi> but to <hi>hurt</hi> the Lord; to fight for falſhood againſt truth, for wrong and iniurie againſt iuſtice, for Poperie and Superſtition againſt Religion; Who as they are guiltie of the ſinne of <hi>Meroz,</hi> ſo ſhall the curſe of <hi>Meroz</hi> vndoubtedly light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. For the Lord hath ſaid it, whoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3159:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>is vnchangeable, whoſe wiſdome is inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable, and whoſe power is vnreſiſtable.</p>
                  <p>Be it farre from me <hi>(my Lords)</hi> to bring you within the compaſſe of this <hi>curſe,</hi> whoſe integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath beene approued both of God and man. We were vnthankfull if we ſhould not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that your Lordſhips haue marched valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this battaile of Iuſtice, and haue alreadie dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped your feet in the bloud of Gods enemies.</p>
                  <p>Yet muſt you conſider that the Cananites are like the Monſter <hi>Hydra,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hydra.</note> wherewith <hi>Hercules</hi> did fight, who when he had cut off one head, another did ſtill ariſe in his place. Wherefore let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to come and <hi>helpe the Lord</hi> afreſh in this battell. <hi>Vp Debbora, ariſe Barack thou ſonne of Abionam, and leade thy captiuitie captiue.</hi> Set vpon the reliques of the Cananites, and firſt thoſe obſtinate Papiſts, who are left amongſt vs, to be thornes in our ſides, and prickes in our eyes, for our vnthankfulneſſe vnto God.</p>
                  <p>I know the Lawes of our Land doe deale fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably with thoſe wilfull Recuſants, who will not once come into the Temple with old <hi>Simeon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> that they might imbrace Chriſt; nor once heare the Word preached with <hi>Candaces eunuch,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> that they might be conuerted vnto Chriſt: but are like the deafe Adder, which clappeth one of his eares cloſe vnto the ground, and with his twining tayle ſtoppeth the other, that hee may not heare the voice of the Charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſely. And therefore of them I may ſay little, ſaue onely
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3159:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>wiſh that as they refuſe to come into our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches when they are aliue, ſo they might haue the buriall of an Aſſe, and their carkaſſes be throwne vpon a dunghill after they are dead.</p>
                  <p>But for the Prieſts and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> who like the Diuell <hi>goe about continually,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> in ſecret corners, <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whom they may deuoure,</hi> who labour to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the hearts of the people from their naturall Soueraigne, vnto <hi>Iabin</hi> of Rome, it is high time to take the nayle of the Lawes into your left hand, and the hammer of execution into your right, and to pierce the head of Popiſh <hi>Siſeraes;</hi> yea double and redouble your blowes vpon them, vntill you haue quite nayled them vnto the ground: which if you doe, the bleſſing of Iſrael ſhall light vpon you, and the power of <hi>Iabin</hi> the Prince of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be much weakened in this our Land.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh daughter Babylon, worthie to be deſtroyed, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall he be that taketh thy children, and daſheth them againſt the ſtones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another ſort of wicked Cananites there are, no leſſe dangerous then the former, I meane thoſe cruell <hi>Oppreſſours,</hi> who by their power, riches and friends doe oppreſſe the poore in the gate; and that which is moſt horrible, vnder the colour of iuſtice, by tyring them out by long and tedious courſes of Law. This is a crying ſinne, which ringeth in the eares of God, and doth certainely draw downe vengeance vpon a Land, if it be not reformed.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.12.</note> For <hi>when the Lord maketh inquiſition for bloud, he remembreth it, and forgetteth not the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3159:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>complaint of the poore.</hi> By how much the more all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, who are gods,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.</note> ſhould in this imitate God, namely in taking vengeance vpon oppreſſours, and in deliuering the poore out of their hands. The glorious Throne of <hi>Salomon</hi> which was made of Iuory and couered with gold,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 10.19, 20.</note> had ſtayres to leane vpon, which were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, Lyons, &amp; hands curiouſly wrought; to ſignifie (as ſome thinke) that it is the duetie of a good Prince and Magiſtrate to be a couragious Lyon to deſtroy oppreſſours, and to be a hand of ſuccour to relieue the wronged.</p>
                  <p>Surely, oppreſſion is the rifeſt ſinne in this land. Let a man caſt his eyes vnto all iudiciall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and it commonly falleth out, <hi>Pauper vbi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acet,</hi> the weaker goes lightly to the walls.</p>
                  <p>There is a prettie <hi>Embleme</hi> in <hi>Alciat:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Piſsicules aurata rapit medio aequore Sardas:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſilly Sprats beeing vnder the Water, are chaſed vp and downe by the great <hi>gilt heads;</hi> and if they ſpring out of the Sea for feare, they are quickly deuoured of the greedie Seamewes: euen ſo the poore people, if they liue quietly at home, they are iniured by their rich neighbours, and if they ſeeke abroad to be relieued by the Law, they are many times ouerthrowne, though their cauſe be good. And where is the fault? Surely a field may be loſt vnder the conduction of the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captaines.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3159:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> And therefore I muſt intreat alſo the Iuſtices of the Bench to <hi>helpe the Lord</hi> in this buſineſſe. Who as they are like thoſe threeſcore ſtrong men about the bed of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who had euerie one his ſword vpon his thigh for the feare by night,<note place="margin">Cant. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. ſo ſhould they draw out the ſword of their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie as farre as they can, for ſuppreſſing of the wicked, and for defending of the good, that the bed, which is the peace and quietneſſe of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> may be preſerued.</p>
                  <p>What ſhould I ſpeake of Counſailors who are Captaines and Coronels in this battel? Doe they <hi>come to helpe the Lord againſt the mightie?</hi> Yes ſurely, ſo long as they doe faithfully deliuer the Oracles of the Law; but if they helpe to peruert iuſtice, and to turne it into <hi>Wormewood,</hi> eyther by defending falſhood, or impugning the truth, they ioyne with the Cananites againſt the Lord. I am not ignorant how an Heathen Orator ſaid well, That a Iudge muſt alwaies follow the truth, but a Counſailor may preſſe the probalilitie of his Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents cauſe; which I grant in a doubtfull matter to be often true, but when their conſciences doe know that a cauſe is naught, how impious is it then to take ſees, or to giue any counſell to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the truth? Therefore againſt ſuch I muſt pronounce the curſe of <hi>Iude,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iude verſ. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Woe vnto them for they haue gone in the way of Cain,</hi> and runne greedily after the errour of <hi>Balaam for reward, and periſhed in the gain ſaying of Core.</hi> You know that <hi>Balaam</hi> was tepted by the glittering gold of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3159:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Balac</hi> to deuiſe curſed counſell againſt the people of God; but what came of it? The vengeance of God followed him vpon the heeles, and he was ſlaine in the battle by the ſword of <hi>Ioſhua.</hi> Oh then <hi>keepe your tongues from euill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34 13.</note> 
                     <hi>and your lips that they ſpeake no guile.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I may not forget the Iurors and Witneſſes, in whom the chiefeſt ſtrength of the iudiciary bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile doth conſiſt. They are indeed by our Lawes the higheſt Iudges in matter of fact, and therfore I muſt ſay vnto them:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Are your minds ſet vpon righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and doe you iudge the thing that is right, O ye ſons of men?</hi> Do you come hither to helpe the Lord of Heauen, or rather to pleaſure and gratifie your earthly Lords? Doe you come with ſingle and conſcionable hearts to further iuſtice, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with partiall and corrupt affections to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert iudgement? I would to God you were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent (my Brethren) but ſure, an <hi>euill report,</hi> and ſcandalous is gone out of you. It is ſaid (I know not how truly) that ſome of you haue <hi>meritorias linguas,</hi> as a falſe Empreſſe did falſely obiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a good Philoſopher; that is, you are corrupted with coyne to ſpeake and to ſweare either contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or beſides your conſciences. Oh then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that of <hi>Iob:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>The congregation of the hypocrite ſhall be deſolate, and fire ſhall deuoure the houſes of bribes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the Prophet fore told that <hi>Manaſſe</hi> ſhould be againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa</hi> 9.21.</note> and both againſt <hi>Iudah;</hi> ſo is there ſuch pulling and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3159:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>halling in Iuries, that ſome are for the plaintife, ſome for the defendant, and both many times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> Of ſuch people, <hi>Chryſostome</hi> excellently ſpeaketh in his fourteenth Homily to the people of Antioch: As little children who with great force draw a long rotten rope contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie waies, doe breake the rope, and failing back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards wound themſelues, ſome in the head, ſome in the ſhoulders, and ſome in other parts of their bodie: Euen ſo they that ſtriuing in iudgement to contrarie purpoſes doe breake the religion of an oath, doe dangerouſly wound their ſoules, and both drop downe into the bottomleſſe gulfe of Periu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie; who when they lay their hands vpon the Booke to ſweare,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.2.</note> would to God they would remember that <hi>flying Booke</hi> in the 5. of <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> which being twentie cubits long, and ten cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits broad, was full of curſes and woes againſt them that ſweare falſly; yea ſuch curſes as ſhould remaine in the midſt of their houſes, and conſume both the timber and the ſtones thereof.</p>
                  <p>Surely, it makes my fleſh to tremble, and my tongue to cleaue vnto the roofe of my mouth, when I conſider that after ſo many yeares preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law, as it were with thunder and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and of preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel as from mount <hi>Sion,</hi> there ſhould be ſo little account made of ſwearing and forſwearing as yet there is. <hi>Oh tell it not in Cath, nay publiſh it not in the ſtreets of Askelon, lest the daughters of the Philiſtims reioyce, lest the vncircumciſed be glad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3159:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Plinie,</hi> who was a great Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Plin.</note> but an Atheiſt; one of the chiefeſt reaſons that perſwaded him there was no God, was becauſe when men were brought into the Capitol of <hi>Rome</hi> to ſweare, and ſtood there before the Image of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> which held a thunderbolt in his hand, as it were to take vengeance of the wicked, yet, ſaith hee, <hi>fulminantem peierant Iouem,</hi> they periured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before <hi>Iupiter</hi> that threatned to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of their periurie. That was but a weake rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to perſwade <hi>Plinie</hi> there was no God; but it is a reaſon to thinke them flat Atheiſts, who taking an oath not by <hi>Iupiter</hi> a falſe God, but by <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> the liuing God, (vnto whom all things are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and open before his eyes) doe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either diſſemble the truth which they are ſworne to reueale; or ouerthrow the truth which they are ſworne to maintain, or ſmother the truth which they are ſworn to bring to light. This is an horrible ſin, and too too common: yet am I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded better things of many of you (beloued Brethren) and ſuch as accompanie ſaluation, and therefore I exhort you in Gods name, that you will iudge iuſtly, <hi>and follow the truth in loue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of any mans perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I haue read in <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> an ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,<note place="margin">Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus.</note> that the old Aegyptians had their Iudges ſet forth in imagerie, in ſuch ſort, that the chiefeſt Iudge had a tablet of Saphire ſtone hanging about his necke, wherein veritie was ingrauen, his eyes were cloſed, and a number of bookes were laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3159:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>him; to note, that a Iudge muſt only reſpect the truth, hauing no regard vnto the perſons, but vnto the cauſe which he muſt carefully learne.</p>
                  <p>But if you ſcorne to learne your dutie of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh people, I commend vnto you the example of holy <hi>Iob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob <hi>29.</hi>
                     </note> who ſaid, and no doubt truely of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being in place of iudgement as you are: <hi>I put on iuſtice and it couered me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 29:14.</note> 
                     <hi>my iudgement was as a robe and a Crowne. I was eyes vnto the blind, and feet vnto the lame, I was a father vnto the poore.</hi> And leſt you ſhould thinke he was more pittifull then iuſt, marke what followeth, <hi>And when I knew not a cauſe, I diligently ſought it out.</hi> Thus if you doe, the eare that heares you ſhall bleſſe you, and the eye that ſees you, ſhall witneſſe vnto you, and the bleſſing of him that is readie to periſh ſhall come vpon you. But if on the other ſide, you ſhal either <hi>take a reward to hurt the innocent, or hinder the right of the Stranger, the widow, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe,</hi> yea or <hi>doe this worke of the Lord negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> and vnfaithfully, <hi>Curſed ſhall you be in the field, and curſed in the towne; curſed ſhall bee your basket and your dowe. Curſed ſhall be the fruit of your bodies, the fruit of your Land, the increaſe of your Kine, and the flockes of your ſheepe.</hi> In a word, <hi>all the curſes of the Law,</hi> like ſo many thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts ſhall light vpon you, and <hi>Let all the people ſay, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3159:17"/>
                  <p>A SERMON OF PATIENCE. Preached at S. <hi>Maries</hi> in Oxford, BY EDWARD GEE, Then Fellow of <hi>Braſen-noſe</hi> Colledge. Since Doctor of Diuinitie, and one of his MAIESTIES Chaplaines in Ordinarie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And now publiſhed for the benefit of others:</hi> BY his two brethren, IOHN GEE and GEORGE GEE, Miniſters of Gods Word.</p>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi>-gate, at the ſigne of the Pyde Bull. 1620.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3159:18"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3159:18"/>
                  <head>A SERMON OF PATIENCE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>IAMES 5. VERS. 7.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Be patient therefore, Brethren, vnto the comming of the Lord: Behold the Husbandman waiteth &amp;c.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S they that build in friths and armes of the Sea (right Worſhipfull and well beloued) doe at a low water fortifie the place with ſome ſtrong wire to keep away the tide, leſt their worke ſhould be ouercome by the reflowing O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean: euen ſo the children of God, who are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to be builded vpon the earth, as in the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſea of troubles and afflictions, muſt in the tranquillitie of their mind, ſence themſelues with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3159:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>the inexpugnable bulwarke of <hi>Patience,</hi> leſt when croſſes doe happen (which happen at one time or other vnto all,) the deepes of heauineſſe breaking out, ſhould ouerflow their ſoules, and beare downe the precious edifice of faith and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie begun in them. The which poynt of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome wiſhing to be rooted in your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous breaſts, I haue made choyce of theſe words of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> wherein he doth ſweetly comfort the poore Chriſtians of his time, who being <hi>as Lillies among the Thornes,</hi> were pricked and rent with the iniuries and oppreſſions of their fellow brethren.<note place="margin">Prou.</note> And albeit this my Text may ſeeme to be like vnto that Wine <hi>Salomon</hi> aduiſed to <hi>giue</hi> onely <hi>to thoſe that haue griefe of heart,</hi> that <hi>drinking they may forget their pouertie,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their miſerie no more; yet, if by your patient attention you ſhall ſhew that you loue and imbrace this excellent vertue of patience, I ſhal, by the aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, make it plain, that euerie one which heareth mee, may receiue ſome wholſome inſtruction out of this Text, wherein there be contained</p>
                  <p>Two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Exhortation; <hi>Bee patient, Brethren.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Motiue of this patience, which is the fountain of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian comfort, namely,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 1.6:7.</note> 
                        <hi>The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord,</hi> when as <hi>he ſhall recompence tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation vnto them that trouble, and vnto them that are troubled, reſt.</hi> But becauſe fleſh and bloud
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3159:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>being impatient of delay, will ſtraight reply, Oh but that day is farre hence, and the hope thereof being deferred, is the fainting of the heart; hee therefore meeteth with that exception by a double reaſon, the one taken from the example of Husbandmen who doe patiently <hi>waite for the former and later raine, to receiue onely the fruit of the earth:</hi> the reddition of which compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing implyed, is, that we ſhould much more pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expect the great harueſt of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we that now <hi>gee weeping and ſow precious ſeede,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6.</note> 
                        <hi>ſhall ioyfully reape</hi> the bleſſed ſheaues of immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. In the other reaſon, he vtterly denyeth the obiection, and vrgeth, that the comming of the Lord is neere at hand, and ſo iterateth his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, incouraging them to be patient, and to ſettle their hearts.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>This I take to be the true meaning and moſt naturall <hi>analyſis</hi> of my Text: all the parts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I intend not particularly to handle at this time, but in the exhortation to inſert the reaſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were the ſinewes and bones wherein the ſtrength and vigour of the exhortation doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then wee muſt vnderſtand, that this holy <hi>patience</hi> whereunto the Apoſtle doth ſtirre vs vp, is not a quiet ſufferance of euils ariſing either from a ſenceleſſe ſtupiditie of the mind which is but brutiſh, or from ſome morall good end which is but Heatheniſh, or from ſome bad and euill pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe which is but diuelliſh;<note place="margin">Definitio.</note> but it is a ſacred ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3159:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſlip of charitie, engraffed in vs by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, wherby we entirely ſubmitting our wils vnto the will of God, doe chearefully beare all wrongs, croſſes, and afflictions, without grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at men, or repining at God; and that for the glorie of his name, for the benefit of his Church, and for the performance of his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>The which heroicall vertue being farre aboue the reach of mans naturall powers, it pleaſed the Lord to teach by a rare example, the wonder and aſtoniſhment of all ages. For behold he that was impaſſible, and could ſuffer nothing did as it were euacuate himſelfe, that he might ſuffer all things, and become a perfect mirrour of patience for vs to behold: whoſe onely death, if it be duely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is moſt effectuall to appeaſe all vnquiet and tumultuous humors in our hearts.</p>
                  <p>What contumelies did he ſuffer? what iniuries did he endure? what torments did he beare? and yet neuer complained,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſay</hi> 33.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.67. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8.23.</note> but ſtood as a harmeleſſe <hi>Sheepe before the Shearer, not opening his mouth.</hi> They reprochfully ſpit vpon his face, who had a little before reſtored the blind by his ſpittle. They reuiled that name, which maketh all creatures, both Angels,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9.10. <hi>Math.</hi> 27.29.</note> and men, and Diuels to tremble. They buffeted him with the palmes of their hand, and crowned him with thornes, who crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his children with garlands of glorie, and putteth palmes of victorie into their hands. They ſtripped him of his robes, and gaue him gall and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3159:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>vinegar to drinke,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 27.31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.28.</note> that had drunken vnto them the cup of the new Teſtament in his bloud, and had prepared a robe of righteouſneſſe to cloathe them withall. Laſtly, they excruciated that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſoule with moſt exquiſite torments vpon the croſſe, which bare their ſorrows,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 53.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.51. <hi>Mark.</hi> 15.33.</note> and carried their infirmities. And though the ſtarres were aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the elements troubled, the earth trembled, and the Sunne withdrew his beames, as loathing to ſee that horrible act; yet was not he touched with any ſparke of anger againſt his perſecutors,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.34.</note> but mildly prayed in their behalfe, <hi>Father, forgiue them, for they know not what they doe.</hi> O more then admirable patience of the Sonne of GOD, whoſe conſtant enduring of that bloudie bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, cannot but animate the faithfull ſouldiers of Chriſt manfully to incounter with all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>In the 1. <hi>Macch.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mach.</hi> 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Antiochus</hi> ſhewed the bloud of Grapes and Mulberries vnto the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants to prouoke them to fight; And the holy Ghoſt, in like ſort, to incourage vs patiently to endure all the calamities of this life, doth poynt vnto the bloudie paſſions of our <hi>Meſsias.</hi> And hence it is that <hi>Peter</hi> proclaimeth, <hi>Chriſt hath ſuffered for vs, leauing vs an example that wee ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> In which ſteps all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyrs and Confeſſors, the Ancient-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of our Faith and dubbed Knights of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt (as <hi>Niſſen</hi> calleth them) haue troden, not <hi>louing their liues vnto the death;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3159:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>enduring, ſome of them to be conſumed in the fire, ſome of them to be ſcalded with boyling lead, ſome of them to be torne in pieces with the racke, ſome of them to be ground in the teeth of wild beaſts; and all of them to ſhed their bloud for the profeſſion of this faith, which hath beene diſſeminated into all parts of the world, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the conſtancie of their profeſſion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this reſiſtance vnto bloud is not as yet fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vnto our ſhare, though God knowes how ſoone all of vs may be put vnto it:</p>
                  <p>I will leaue that part of patience which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in perſecutions, and ſpeake of that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue continuall vſe now in the peace and quietneſſe of the Church; wherein we had need of patience and longanimitie both towards our brethren, and towards our heauenly Father: the former whereof driueth from vs all anger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reuenge againſt thoſe who haue done vs harme; the latter remoueth out of our minds all murmuring againſt God in afflictions ſent imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from him, and cauſeth vs meekely to wait for the complement of his promiſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then, we muſt behaue our ſelues patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards ſuch as haue wronged vs, whether it be in our goods, or names, our dignities, or any thing elſe; not onely refrayning our hands from returning of violence, our tongues from ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, our eyes from irefull lookes, but euen our hearts alſo from any thought or deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3159:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> Thus farre Philoſophie could neuer go; though <hi>Plotinus</hi> ſpeake of vertues,<note place="margin">Plotinus.</note> both <hi>purgatoriae</hi> and <hi>purgati animi,</hi> yet neither of them both could thus farre cleare the ſight of vnderſtanding, to know that euerie motion of wrath is a ſinne; but the wiſdome of God which framed man in his perfection, muſt needs come downe from heauen to reframe him in his defection, and teach this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth doctrine to carnall eares,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 5.22, 23.</note> that <hi>to be angrie with a Brother vnaduiſedly, maketh a man culpable of a iudgement; and to call a Brother Racha makes him worthie to be puniſhed by a Counſell; and to ſay vnto a Brother Foole, deſerues no leſſe then hell fire;</hi> That we muſt loue <hi>them that hate vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 5.44.</note> 
                     <hi>bleſſe them that curſe vs, pray for them that perſecute vs, doe good vnto them that hurt vs, and are our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> all ſtrange aphoriſmes to fleſh and bloud. And yet our Sauiour did not onely command them,<note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>45.</hi>
                     </note> but demonſtrate them alſo by the example of our Father in the Heauens, who ſhowers down his bleſſings vpon both good and bad, his friends and his foes. So that as a Father loues that childe onely in whoſe face he ſeeth the forme, the linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſimilitude of himſelfe; ſo will GOD neither loue nor yet acknowledge any for his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate childe, whoſe heart is not ſtamped with this character of extraordinarie charitie.</p>
                  <p>Here then the Prince of Philoſophers is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted to be blind,<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> who thought that to reuenge iniuries is a part of magnanimitie: and <hi>Scylla,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Scylla.</note> the Romaine Captaine may be noted of vanitie, who
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3159:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>thought it a great glorie to haue it engrauen vpon his tombe, That neuer any man exceeded him in doing miſchiefe vnto his enemies.</p>
                  <p>But, alaſſe, what maruell if thoſe Heathens were ſo fowly deceiued, and ſo vehemently infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the fire of reuenge, ſithence that they who profeſſe themſelues the Schollers of Chriſt, can hardly brooke the Doctrine of patience, but are euen readie to ſay with the Capernaitanes, <hi>This is a hard ſpeech,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.60.</note> 
                     <hi>who can endure it?</hi> or if they lend their eare vnto it for an houre, yet doe they ſcarcely practiſe it once in their whole life. Nay would to God that we whom wiſdome and a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer knowledge of Chriſt ſhould purifie from all corrupt affections, were free from inordinate wrath, and a ſecret practiſe of reuenge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cato,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cato.</note> the Cenſour, was wont to ſay, not ſo much vpon pride, as being conſcious of his owne knowledge, that if other men offended they were to be borne with, becauſe they did it vpon igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or impotencie of affections; but if himſelfe committed a fault, it was to be imputed to meere malice, and therefore deſerued no pardon. In like ſort may it be ſaid of this impatience, that if the vnlearned doe ſinne therein, it is more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; but if we that are not onely inſtructed in the Arts of humanitie, but alſo in the knowledge of diuine myſteries, and are as Lampes to giue light vnto others, be faultie herein, ſure our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice muſt needes be exceeding great, and our fault more hainous before God and man.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3159:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> Placabilitie and meekeneſſe ſhould alwaies at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon wiſdome,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14.</note> euen as the Virgines follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Queene <hi>in a veſture of Needle-worke, Pſ.</hi> 45. And therefore Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in the third Chapter of this Epiſtle asketh,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Is any man wiſe and endued with knowledge amongſt you? Let him ſhew by good conuerſation his workes in meekeneſſe of wiſdome.</hi> Wherefore, art thou a ruler and haſt the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of people? Then haſt thou plentifull mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of exerciſing thy patience.<note place="margin">Xenophon.</note> For <hi>Xenophon</hi> hath well obſerued in the Preface of his Hiſtorie, that men are more bitter and trouble ſome vnto their rulers than any flocke of Sheepe or heard of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell vnto their leaders; which <hi>Moſes</hi> the mildeſt man that euer was proued to be true, whoſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was ſo moued with the vntowardneſſe of his vnruly multitude, that when he came out of the Mount <hi>Horeb,</hi> hauing talked ſo familiarly with God that his face ſhone as the Sunne; yet ſeeing the people commit idolatrie, in a great rage he brake in pieces the Tables of the law,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19.</note> which were written by Gods owne Fingers. And indeed this is a godly and zealous impatience, not to endure the iniuries and diſhonors of God, but to reuenge them with all ſeueritie. Nay thou muſt be impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient alſo in the wrongs done vnto thy brethren, like as <hi>Abraham</hi> who ayded <hi>Lot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.16.</note> to recouer his goods of the fiue Kings; for in this caſe true is that of the Heathen,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                     <hi>Si non propulſas iniuriam cum potes, facis:</hi> Thou art as much in fault as he that doth the wrong, if thou redreſſe it not.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3159:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> But if thou draw the ſword of thy authoritie out of the ſcabbard to reuenge thy priuate iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and diſlikes, how doeſt thou obay his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, who ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom</hi> 12.19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.</note> 
                     <hi>Auenge not your ſelues, but giue place vnto wrath?</hi> for it is written, <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is mine, and I will repay, ſaith the Lord, Ro.</hi> 12. Yea much more blame worthy art thou, if thou be like vnto that furious Houſholder which the ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> deſcribeth,<note place="margin">Ecclus. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 4. <hi>Be not as a Lyon in thine houſe, neither beat thy ſeruants for thy fancie, nor oppreſſe them that are vnder thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh but they are ſuch as doe alwaies withſtand my will,<note place="margin">Ob. Sol.</note> and therefore I cannot endure it. Why, if thou haue this Chriſtian patience which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> doth here commend, it will repreſſe in thee all ſuch thoughts and affections, and thou wilt not ſo much labour to wreſt other mens wils vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine, as to compoſe and ſubmit thine owne will vnto Gods, which is, that lenitie and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>ſhould be knowne vnto all men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. where the Apoſtle vſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifieth, that wee ſhould deale with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and not in extremity of right to reuenge our wrongs.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Caius Caeſar</hi> was Dictator in Rome,<note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> and <hi>Metellus</hi> the Tribune in a matter reſiſted his will, <hi>Caeſar</hi> being not a whit offended, replyed, <hi>Nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. efficies vt iam Caeſaris mereare,</hi> Thou ſhalt neuer prouoke <hi>Caeſar</hi> to be angrie at thee. A noble ſpeech of a Heathen Magiſtrate, who hauing but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3159:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>driuen <hi>Pompey</hi> out of Italie, and brought ſome legions of ſouldiers into the Citie, thought it a baſe thing to ſeeke reuenge of one that was infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour vnto himſelfe; And ſhall not a Chriſtian Gouernour who hath vanquiſhed the powers of darkeneſſe, and ſubdued many legions of Diuels, carrie himſelfe farre more vprightly then once to thinke of hurting or moleſting them that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his iuriſdiction? eſpecially conſidering that <hi>the iudge is at the doore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.9.</note> readie to drop downe the viols of vengeance vpon their heads, who will needes take vengeance out of his hands.</p>
                  <p>Some Philoſophers doe write,<note place="margin">Plinius in Hiſt. natur.</note> that the Bee in ſtinging doth with ſuch violence thruſt out her ſting, that whiles ſhe labours to hurt her enemy, ſhe deſtroyes her ſelfe; and therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> in his Booke of Clemencie doth wiſh,<note place="margin">Senec. lib. de Clementia.</note> that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men were alike, and that ſuch as ſtudie to annoy others, might doe it to their owne hurt: But <hi>Seneca</hi> might haue ſpared that wiſh; for we know (my Brethren) that he who ſeeketh to hurt any of the children of men (although his enemie)<note place="margin">47.</note> doth not onely diſarme himſelfe of his ſpirituall weapons, but alſo killeth and deſtroyeth his own ſoule; So that we had need (as our Sauiour wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his Apoſtles) <hi>by patience to poſſeſſe our ſoules,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.19.</note> without which we ſhall euerie moment loſe and make ſhipwracke thereof.</p>
                  <p>But art thou a priuate man, vnder the rule of ſome oppeſſing <hi>Rheoboam,</hi> whoſe little finger is as heauie vnto thee, as any mans loynes? who whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3159:24"/>thee not with roddes, but with ſcorpions. Here then thou muſt beware of hating him whom the Lord hath placed ouer thee, although he be vnto thee as a Lyon or a Beare. <hi>Quid odiſſet Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium Milo materiam ac ſegetem ſuae gloriae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero in orat. pro Milone.</note> ſaith <hi>Tullie,</hi> How could <hi>Milo</hi> hate <hi>Clodius</hi> who was the matter and the ſubiect of his glorie? And wilt thou being a Chriſtian, hate him who is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thy eternall glorie, if thou endure it for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake? nay, rather take the aduice of the wiſe Preacher,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10. <hi>When the ſpirit of thy ruler is incenſed against thee, containe thy ſelfe modestly within thy dutie. Nam homo ſanans ſedat peccata multa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iunius in loc.</note> as <hi>Iunius</hi> doth well tranſlate it; that is, If thou labour by a dutifull ſubmiſſion to mitigate the furie of the ruler, thou ſhalt both ſtop many ſins which otherwiſe hee would commit, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent a miſchiefe which would light vpon thine owne head, as the Verſes following doe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ſhew; But if his heart be hardened daily more and more againſt thee, as was the heart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by ſome ſecret iudgement of God: Oh then ſettle thine owne heart, and remember that <hi>the patient abiding of the poore ſhall not periſh for euer.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>37.</hi>
                     </note> Remember how the ſoules of Martyrs which lay vnder the altar, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6. cried, ſaying, <hi>How long,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, which are holy and true, doeſt thou not iudge and auenge our bloud on them that dwell on the earth?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> but it was replyed, <hi>That they ſhould rest for a little ſeaſon vntill the number of their fellow-brethren was fulfilled.</hi> The which bleſſed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3159:24"/>ſpirits did crie for reuenge, not vpon any priuate perturbation, but vpon an holy deſire of ſeeing the iuſtice of God accompliſhed: the which medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocritie becauſe wee that are cloathed with this earthly Tabernacle, cannot keepe, wee muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all deſire of reuenge, and tarrie the Lords leaſure to be ſtrong,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>37.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and he will comfort our hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But becauſe infinite are the occaſions of iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and diſcontentment amongſt priuate men, which being eſteemed as iniuries, doe ſtir vp chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler &amp; debate, let vs conſider the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of Chriſt [<hi>that we ſhould loue one another:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.34.</note>] which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſong was no ſooner begun of our Sauiour, the ſweeteſt <hi>praecenter</hi> that euer tuned Note, but ſtraight-waies followed the whole Quire of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Euangeliſts, deſcanting the ſame Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and filling euerie Page of their Epiſtles and Goſpels with precepts of Charitie. The which Charitie, if it be in vs as hote and feruent as it ſhould, it would ſwallow vp all the iniuries that are done vnto vs, euen as a flaming fire which burns more vehemently when ſome drops of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are caſt therein. And herehence it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> weauing as it were for vs a rich and glorious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the purple wooll of the meeke Lambe of God, commandeth vs to <hi>put on the bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                     <hi>kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekeneſſe, patience, forbearing one another, and forgiuing one another, if any man haue a quarrell againſt another.</hi> This is a faire and goodly coate, ſeruing vs both
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3159:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>for indument to couer our nakedneſſe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniment alſo to defend vs from wrongs. For he that hath thoſe two vertues, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Gentleneſſe, and Longanimitie, will doe no wrong, and yet patiently endure the iniuries of others.</p>
                  <p>But,<note place="margin">Applica.</note> alaſſe, now in theſe latter dayes, wherein ſelfe loue hath quite deuoured the loue of Chriſt and our Brethren, ſo nice and touchous are men become, that they cannot endure the ſmalleſt wrongs; nay the fumes ariſing from their teſtie and boyling ſtomacks, do ſo diſturbe their heads, the ſeate and throne of iudgement, that euerie trifle ſeemeth an iniurie to be proſecuted by rigor of Law, nay by fire and ſword; or if abilitie and oportunitie be wanting, at leaſt by irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able hate.</p>
                  <p>I deny not but if thou ſee that thy forbearance doth make thy enemie ſtill more inſolent, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Poets ſaying doth come to paſſe, <hi>Veterem ferendo iniuriam inuitas nouam,</hi> By bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the old iniurie thou draweſt on a new: then mayeſt thou with good conſcience ſeeke redreſſe of the Magiſtrate, ſo thy minde be free from acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitie of reuenge, and onely intentiue vpon the iuſt defence of thy ſelfe. As for the other two ſorts of priuate reuenge, they ought to be farre from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Chriſtian heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> Yea, but what if thou canſt get no redreſſe by the Law? What if a mightier than thy ſelfe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thee? What if the mind of the Iudges be not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3159:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> ſet vpon equitie and right, but <hi>turne Iustice into Wormewood, and repell the iuſt complaint of the poore?</hi> Sure if this come to paſſe, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, beeing a vanitie as old as <hi>Salomon. I haue ſeene</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the place of iudgement where was wickedneſſe, and the place of iuſtice where was ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, Eccleſ.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.16.</note> And therefore himſelfe giues an Antidote againſt the poyſon, <hi>cap.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>If in a Countrie thou ſeest the oppreſsion of the poore, and the defrauding of iudgement and iustice, be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonied at the matter, for he that is higher then the higheſt, regardeth; and there be higher then they.</hi> Here then, if thou take vnto thee <hi>Patience,</hi> it will diſpell all the anguiſh of thy ſoule, like vnto that wood wherewith <hi>Moſes</hi> made <hi>the bitter waters of Marah ſweet</hi> and pleaſant:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.23. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> which thou mayſt the better doe, if thou lift vp thine eyes into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and conſider that GOD regardeth, and will in time make thee a full ſatisfaction for all thy wrongs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath made an excellent Treatiſe of <hi>Patience,</hi> full of fragrant and odoriferous flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,<note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> whereof one is fit vnto this purpoſe; <hi>Satis i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneus est patientiae ſequeſter Deus, ſi iniuriam depoſueris penes eum, vltor eſt, ſi damnum reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor eſt, ſi dolorem medicus eſt, ſi mortem reſuſcita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor est;</hi> Oh well is thee if thou make GOD the Vmpier of thy patience. If thou putteſt thy iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries into his hands, he will be thy auenger; if thy loſſes, he will be thy reſtorer; if thy diſeaſes, hee will be thy Phyſitian; if thy death, he will be thy
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3159:26"/>rayſer vp againe: ſo that thou ſhalt be ſure to haue iuſtice, either at the end of thy life when thou goeſt vnto the Lord, or at the day of iudgement when the Lord ſhall come vnto thee.</p>
                  <p>Antiquitie did report, that <hi>Achilles</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, which the Greekes did vniuſtly award vnto ſlie <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> were in a Shipwracke loſt in the Sea, and after by the waues thereof carryed vnto the Troian ſhore, and layd vpon the Tombe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iax</hi> that had beſt right vnto them; which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a fable or true Hiſtory, it skils not much; the Poets thereby would repreſent the courſe of Iuſtice, which at the length preuaileth and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the vpper hand. But we haue a more ſure word <hi>(my Brethren)</hi> both of the Prophets and of Chriſt himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19.</note> that a day of refreſhing wil come, and that euerie man ſhall be rewarded according to his workes; the remembrance whereof makes vs to beare all oppreſſion and tribulation with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacritie, <hi>knowing that theſe light afflictions which continue but for a moment,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</note> 
                     <hi>doe bring with them a farre more excellent and eternall weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Olympian combats, he wan the garland that beſtowed moſt blows vpon his fellow cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion; but in the Liſts of Chriſt, where GOD is our <hi>Agonotheta,</hi> or Rewarder, the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels our Spectators, the holy Ghoſt our Annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; he beares away the Crowne that beares pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently the blowes of his aduerſarie, and in liew thereof, returneth nothing but good turnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3159:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>he plainely ſhewes thereby that his enemie did beat the ayre onely, and neuer touch him with his wrongs. Which kind of conflict, mans nature will better endure, if he doe conſider, that his caſe who doth harme his brother, is farre worſe then he that receiueth wrong as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doth well obſerue. Was not the adulterous wife of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiphar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>39:</hi>
                     </note> though ietting in her Palace, farre more wretched and worſe tormented then <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the Stockes? Was not wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> in more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate, then poore <hi>Naboth</hi> that loſt both his Vineyard and his life? Yes ſurely:<note place="margin">1. <hi>King</hi> 21.</note> and ſo it is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie iniurie alike, wherein the actor at one time or other time is vexed in his minde; but he that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth hath matter of ioy, when he conſidereth that his ſufferings doe come from the wil of God, and ſo doth remit all anger againſt thoſe that are the doers thereof:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.</note> like as good <hi>Dauid</hi> did pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently beare the reproches of <hi>Shemei,</hi> when he conſidered that the finger of the Lord was therin, and remembred that though his good name were abuſed, yet the Lord would, through his conſtant enduring, <hi>make his righteouſneſſe as cleare as the light, and his iuſt dealing as the noone-day.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.6.</note> And thus let euerie one, as <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21.</note> learne, <hi>not to be ouercome of euill, but to ouercome euill with goodneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>The ſecond part, <hi>Of patience toward God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>2</label> NOw it remaineth that I ſhould ſpeake of that <hi>Patience</hi> which we are to vſe toward God,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3159:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>which how neceſſarie it is, will eaſily appeare, if we conſider that no part of the worſhip of GOD can be without it.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Leuit.</hi> 2.13.</note> For as no ſacrifice could be without ſalt, ſo can no part of Religion be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aright without this patience. Witneſſe the hearing of the Word preached, the doore and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance vnto life; which if it be not patiently conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued vnto the end, what will it bring but that curſe;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.9.</note> 
                        <hi>He that withdraweth his eare from hearing the Word, his Prayer is abhominable?</hi> Witneſſe the practiſe of godly life, which if it be impatiently broken off, doth heare, <hi>The dogge is returned to his vomit,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.22.</note> 
                        <hi>and the Sow that was waſhed to the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the myre.</hi> Witneſſe our inuocation and prayers,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>88.</hi>
                        </note> which, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> notes vpon the 88. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> are many times repelled of God, that as a flame of fire which is blowne backward, they may returne and be more ardent; and therefore vnleſſe they patiently proceed, they neuer draw downe any bleſſing of God. Witneſſe our loue, which if by patience it burne not to the end, wee ſhall heare a <hi>woc</hi> ſounding from heauen, becauſe <hi>we haue forſaken our firſt loue.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.4.</note> Witneſſe our hope, which though it be <hi>the Anchor of the ſoule,</hi> yet is patience the cable which ties it faſt vnto the ioyes of Heauen,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.25.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth: <hi>If we hope for that we ſee not, we doe with patience abide for it, Rom.</hi> 8. And therefore if patience bee taken away, the ſhip of Faith muſt needes be ouerthrowne and daſhed vpon the rockes of deſpaire. Thus is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the pillar that ſupporteth euery good work,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3159:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>which as it is requiſite at all times, ſo eſpecially in the euill day and time of affliction. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit wee are taught out of Gods Word, that our heauenly Father doth chaſtiſe thoſe ſonnes whom hee will receiue,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.</note> but lets the Baſtards and Runnagates goe free; albeit GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath promiſed that hee will not fayle his People, neither forſake his Inheritance,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</note> yet ſuch is our impatient nature, that wee are readie to murmure at GOD, either becauſe he ſends vs ſuch afflictions, or elſe becauſe hee deliuers vs not ſo ſoone as we expect. Hence doth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> admoniſh vs in the 37.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.7.</note> 
                        <hi>Pſalme, Waite patiently vpon the Lord, and hope on him;</hi> or as the Originall doth ſound, <hi>Be ſilent vnto the Lord.</hi> Which word doth excellently expreſſe that ſetling of the mind, and quietneſſe of affections, which in their tribulation the children of GOD muſt enioy.</p>
                     <p>Behold holy <hi>Iob,</hi> the excellent Champion of God, and thou ſhalt ſee, as in a cleare glaſſe, this religious ſilence of mind: Behold, a more victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conquerour ſitting vpon a dung-hill, than <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the Great vpon his chayre of Eſtate: for the Spirit of GOD hath ſaid it;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.32.</note> 
                        <hi>Hee that is ſlow to anger is better than the mightie Man, and hee that ruleth his owne minde is better than he that winneth a Citie, Prou.</hi> 16. Behold what variety of euill tydings, like fearefull cracks of Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der did ſtrike the eares of this inexpugnable for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, and yet could they make no breach into
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3159:28"/>his ſoule. The firſt was his orbitie and loſſe of children; the ſecond his pouertie and loſſe of riches, both able to haue burſt a heart of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, and yet made they not the leaſt ſcarre in his ſoule.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne againe; the Lord gaue, and the Lord hath taken away, now bleſſed be the name of the Lord. In all this did not Iob ſinne, nor charge God fooliſhly with his lippes.</hi> Yea but peraduenture he will impatiently breake forth, if his skinne be touched vnto the quicke. Oh loathſome Lazar,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.7.</note> full of ſore boyles <hi>from the ſole of his foote vnto the crowne of his head,</hi> able to haue made patience it ſelfe waſpiſh and teſtie; and yet though his wife, as bellowes of impatience, did counſaile him to <hi>curſe GOD and die,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>9.</hi>
                        </note> yet <hi>did he not ſinne with his lippes,</hi> but mildly replyes, <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt like a fooliſh Woman;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>10.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>What? ſhall we receiue good at the hand of GOD, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue euill?</hi> Yea though his friends like prickes and thornes in his ſide, did euer pierce his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoule; though theſe intollerable griefs ſhould continue vpon him vnto his death, yet would he ſtill patiently expect:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
                        <hi>All the dayes of mine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time will I waite vntill my changing ſhall come,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cap.</hi> 19.25.</note> 
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. Yea, <hi>I am ſure that my Redeemer liueth, and he ſhall ſtand laſt vpon the earth, and though after my skinne Wormes deſtroy this bodie, yet ſhall I ſee GOD in my fleſh, Cap.</hi> 19. Oh dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe patience, which would neuer once ſhrinke vntill the comming of our Lord! and ſhall we
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3159:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>(my Brethren) who haue much more occaſions of comfort than this man had, be deiected by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, by ſickneſſe, by death of friends, by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, or by any other diſcontentment? We know,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> that as men doe cauſe their fineſt linnens which they weare next vnto their skinnes, to bee continually waſhen and wrenched, that they may be pure and cleane from filth, but their ſacks and courſe haire clothes they doe not waſh: euen ſo, the Lord of Hoſtes doth afflict his deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (whom he will take vp into his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome) that they may be cleanſed from ſinne and pollution of the fleſh; but thoſe whom he regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not, he ſuffers to enioy quietneſſe and eaſe. And why then doe not we reioyce in all diſtreſſes, ſeeing we are purged therby as by a ſcouring ſope and purified as the Gold and ſiluer in the fire, that ſo we may be made fit for him that is puritie and holineſſe it ſelfe?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                        </label> Oh, but thou thinkeſt that the Lord who hath ſaid, <hi>Many are the troubles of the righteous,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>34.19.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>but he will deliuer them out of all,</hi> is too too ſlow in performing his promiſe vnto thee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou repineſt at his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhall anſwere thee vpon the 35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> Oh man,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>35.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <note place="margin">Sol.</note> thou art <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ke-man of GOD, and the time of the pay comes after, why then doeſt thou craue thy hire before thou haſt done thy worke? If thy ſeruant would needes be payed before hand, thou wouldeſt be offended with him, becauſe thereby he ſhould ſeeme to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3159:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſtruſt thy fidelitie; and ſhall not God be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with thee, that art ſo haſtie with him who is veritie it ſelfe? A worthie place to repreſſe the feſtination of your diffident nature which loues no delay, and would be at a poynt with GOD to know ſome certaine time of her deliuerie: but the Lord himſelfe hath beaten downe that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of ours,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.16.</note> 
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 28. <hi>Qui credit non praefeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabit,</hi> He that beleeueth will not be too haſtie, but patiently expect the leiſure of our God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Popilius,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Popilius.</note> the Legate of Rome, beeing ſent Ambaſſadour vnto <hi>Antiochus,</hi> drew a circle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him with his ſtaffe, and commanded him to giue an anſwere before he came out of the circle; but our God (my Brethren) is not like vnto <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> that we may preſcribe vnto him a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine compaſſe of time. When the Diſciples of Chriſt were haſtie to know the time of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters glorie, he puts them off with a long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iade of troubles,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> which they were firſt to endure, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. And after his reſurrection, pricked with the ſame deſire,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 1.6.</note> they asked, <hi>Maſter wilt thou at this time reſtore the Kingdome vnto Iſrael?</hi> but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels them with a checke:<note place="margin">verſ <hi>7.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons which the Father hath put in his owne power;</hi> implying that they ſhould pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently rely vpon GODS promiſes, and perſeuer to expect the performance thereof vnto the end, without curious inquiring after the time. This pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient expectance is a ſpeciall effect of a liuely Faith, and was in all the children of God. Looke
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3159:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull; how did the Lord poſt him ouer, and all for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Faith? Though the Lord promiſed him that hee would make him a great Nation,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.28.</note> when he came out of <hi>Vr of the Chaldees,</hi> yet was the performance of that promiſe deferred more then twentie yeares; <hi>Abraham</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill patiently relying vpon God, and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king through all the impediments and obſtacles of his Faith. Looke vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriarch to whom at his firſt going into Padan Syria,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.13.</note> though the Lord promiſed to giue vnto him the Land vpon which he ſlept, when he ſaw the dreame of the heauenly Ladder, yet what difficulties had his faith to ſtriue with, a churliſh vnkle vnder whom he ſerued a long prentiſhip, a bloudie bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeking to take away his life, a poore eſtate to bee a ſilly Shepheard; and notwithſtanding all theſe hinderances, he firmely claue vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of GOD, and ſtriuing with the Angel, was called <hi>Iſrael, preuayling with GOD.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</note> Looke vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe life though it was nothing but a Map of continuall ſorrowes and afflictions, yet doe the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> (wherein a man may ſee the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Anatomie of his ſoule) ſet forth vnto vs his liuely faith, and patient expectance of GODS promiſes.</p>
                     <p>Thus did the faithfull ſeruants of God pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently waite for benefits that were but tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, though ſhadowing vnto them eternall gifts: And ſhall not we (who haue the Kingdome of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3159:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>heauen plainely ſee before vs, without veile or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering) farre more patiently abide all the tempeſts and ſtormes of this life, for the excellent glorie which is reuealed vnto vs by the comming of the <hi>Meſsiah?</hi> Shall wee not be followers of them, who by Faith and Patience doe inherite the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes?</p>
                     <p>If theſe examples cannot moue, let vs looke vnto them who onely reſpect worldly commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and be aſhamed of our owne ſluggiſhmeſſe in thoſe things which concerne the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
                     <p>Behold,<note place="margin">Examp.</note> how doth the <hi>Husbandman</hi> caſt his ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the earth, and endure much labour and toyle, and waite all the ſeaſons of the yeare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can reape his deſired crop? How doe the <hi>Huntſmen</hi> endure hunger, and cold, raine, and ſnow in the Woods and Deſerts, and expect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a long day before they can catch the ſpoyles they ſeeke after? How doth the <hi>Merchant</hi> cut the dangerous Seas in perill of Ship wracke euery houre? what tediouſneſſe doth he ſuffer? what lothſomneſſe doth he ſuftaine before he can bring home the coſtly Merchandice and price from the Indies? What dangers doth the <hi>Warrier</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take? what blowes and wounds doth he quietly put vp? what long ſieges doth he abide before he can take the ſconce or citie of his enemie? And ſhall not we be leſſe wearie, and more patiently ſuffer all hardneſſe to obtaine celeſtiall Ieruſalem, whoſe ſhining is like vnto a ſtone moſt precious,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.11.</note>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3159:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>as a <hi>Iaſpir ſtone,</hi> ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re as <hi>Cryſtall;</hi> to get that Pearle which a man <hi>ſhould ſell all that be hath to buy;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.45.</note> to win thoſe ſpoyles whereof we can neuer be ſpoyled any more, to reape that Corne which makes the bread of eternall life?</p>
                     <p>Men, and Brethren,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.8.</note> ſhall <hi>the Children of this World bee alwayes wiſer in their generation, than wee that are the Children of Light are in ours?</hi> Shall faintneſſe and defatigation tyre vs, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſithence our life is ſo ſhort, and our time ſo vncertaine?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                        </label> But here it may be demaunded, why <hi>Iames</hi> ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs vp vnto <hi>Patience,</hi> vſeth as a Motiue, <hi>the day of the Lord,</hi> and not rather, the day of our death, wherein we ſooner receiue the fruit of our ſufferings?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                        </label> Whereunto I anſwer, that true indeed, <hi>They which dye in the Lord,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.13.</note> 
                        <hi>doe preſently reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them:</hi> neither doth this place make ought for their opinion, who fondly thinke that the ſoules of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous departed, doe ſleepe, feeling neither weyle nor woe vntill the latter day; but hee vſeth the comming of Chriſt vnto iudgement, as being the ſtrongeſt argument of comfort (like as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelfe did, and many other) both becauſe our bliſſe in bodie and ſoule ſhall bee perfectly conſummated at that day, and the iuſtice of God cleared, and all occaſions of impatience remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                     <p>Doeſt thou murmure and repine to ſee the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3159:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>trampled vnder feete, and the wicked glittering with honour and riches here vpon the earth?</p>
                     <p>Oh conſider,<note place="margin">Sinul.</note> that this world is like vnto a field of Corne, wherein the Blew-bottles, and Goul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings with their goodly colours, doe out-face the pureſt Wheat: but ſtay vntill the great Harueſt, when the Angels ſhall come with their ſicles to reape,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>13.</hi>
                        </note> and then ſhalt thou ſee thoſe glorious Weedes bound in bundles, and burned with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire; but the Corne brought with ioy into the Barne of the Lord. Now is the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the World, wherein the Vngodly like Graſſe are greene and flouriſhing, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous being Trees, are naked and vnſeemely, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all their life in the roote; but ſtay vntill the Sommer, when the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe that appeareth meeke and gentle in <hi>Virgo,</hi> ſhall enter into <hi>Leo,</hi> and then ſhalt thou ſee the Graſſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> but the Trees which are <hi>planted by the Riuers of Water,</hi> to be tranſplanted into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens, and being laden with all ſorts of precious fruit, to be placed in the Paradiſe of God. Art thou now offended to ſee the iudgements of God moſt fiercely ſtriking the innocent in this life, and ſuffering the wicked to goe free; Oh ſtay vntill the end, and thou ſhalt ſee iudgement reduced vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iuſtice,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.15.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in the 94. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> And <hi>all them that are true of Heart aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When a piece of Arras is in working,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> it loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth fowle and rude, hauing here a foot and there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3159:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>a head; but being throughly finiſhed, how glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious doth it ſeeme, when we ſee the whole co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence of the worke, and the meaning of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries tapiſtred therein? euen ſo the iudgements of God which are as the great deepes ſeeme yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs crooked and vniuſt, but when the thrones ſhall be ſet, and the Nations ſummoned by a Trumpe, and the Regiſter Bookes of GOD be ſhewed; the mouthes of the wicked ſhall be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and the eyes of the iuſt ſhall be fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. This is a comfortable argument, and of all reaſons the holy Ghoſt vſeth, moſt effectuall to perſwade. But another doubt of greater difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doth offer it ſelfe. For how did <hi>Iames</hi> ſay tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Dub.</note> that the comming of the Lord was neere at hand, ſithence one thouſand fiue hundred yeares are paſſed ſince <hi>Iames</hi> did write, and yet all things continue as they did?</p>
                     <p>I anſwer; <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                        </label> That thoſe words did not import that the Lords day was to come within ſome ſhort and preciſe terme of time, for that opinion <hi>Paul</hi> did purpoſely refute, 2. <hi>Theſſalon.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.</note> But the Scriptures ſay, that the Lords day was neere at hand in three reſpects.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
                        </label> Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for that the continuance of the World after Chriſts birth, ſhall bee ſhorter then it was before.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, in reſpect of God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> with whom (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) a <hi>thouſand yeares are but as one day.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of eternitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3159:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereof all the age of the World ſhall bee leſſe then one drop to the whole Ocean. And in this ſence, the Apoſtle ſaid, that the comming of the Lord is neere at hand; but as for determining any ſet time of the laſt iudgement, the Scripture is altogether ſilent. Nay, it plainely affirmes, that GOD would haue it vnknowne, to the end we ſhould alwaies be in readineſſe, watching <hi>with our loynes girt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.35. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 39.</note> 
                        <hi>and our lampes in our hand.</hi> For <hi>if the good man of the houſe knew when the Theefe would come,</hi> he would onely then keepe watch and ward, but at other times be ſleepie and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. And therefore <hi>CHRIST IESVS</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſired of his Diſciples to tell them ſome ſignes when this day ſhould come, told them, That none might certainly preſage the day, yeare, or any other time; as appeareth, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe the World doth now ſwarme with thoſe euill ſeruants, who ſay in their hearts, <hi>Our Maſter doth deferre his comming,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.45.</note> and <hi>beginne to ſmite their fellowes, and to eate and drinke with the drunken:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>46.</hi>
                        </note> Let them know that their Maſter <hi>will come in a day when they looke not for him, and in an houre when they are not aware, and cut them off, and giue them their portion with Hypocrites in the Lake wherein is nothing but weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth.</hi> And becauſe wee are fallen indeed into <hi>the latter dayes,</hi> and into the times of <hi>mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and ſcornefull Epicures, <hi>walking after their luſts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3: 4.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming?
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3159:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>for ſince the Fathers died, all things continue alike:</hi> Let them remember, that <hi>GOD is not ſtacke as they count ſlackneſſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>9.</hi>
                        </note> but patient to waite for their repentance and amendment of life; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying whereof they doe but whord vp for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vengeance againſt the day of vengeance, and <hi>of the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.</note> and therefore let them take heede leſt this day <hi>come vpon them as a ſnare, while their hearts be oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.35.</note> 
                        <hi>and cares of this life.</hi> But as for you who are <hi>trodden vnder foote, and oppreſſed by the violence of the proud,</hi> looke vp, and ioyfully lift vp your heads, for the day of your redemption draweth neere;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.28.</note> not your redemption from the bondage of Satan, and ſlauerie of ſinne, from which you are alreadie freed by the bloud of Chriſt, but your redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from all the miſeries of this life, which <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Epheſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> A redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of libertie by the glorious appearing of Chriſt, which cannot poſſibly be farre off.</p>
                     <p>Some Mathematicians are of opinion, that the Sun is approached vnto vs, and holdeth his courſe in the firmament neerer vnto the earth by many thouſand miles, than it did heretofore time; as if all elementarie Creatures being now olde, and at the laſt caſt, had need more effectually to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Sunne beames: which howſoeuer it be but a mathematicall fancie; yet it is certaine that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is come neerer vnto vs than euer vnto any of our fore-fathers: nay, the cold &amp; fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3159:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſpoſition of mens minds in this age, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſtian loue is abated, and charitie waxen more then kaye-colde, doth ſufficiently argue that our Sauiour <hi>is euen at the doore.</hi> Behold, the Figge-tree hath budded, and ſhot forth her yong Figges, the Vine hath brought forth Grapes, but the Grapes of <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſuch as muſt come in the laſt dayes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.3.</note> to wit, <hi>Selfe-louers, couetous perſons, boasters, proud, curſed ſpeakers, diſobedient to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, vnthankfull, vnholy, without naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, intemperate, fierce, no louers at all of them that be good, traytors, headie, high-minded, louers of pleaſures more then louers of GOD, hauing a ſhew of godlineſſe, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the power thereof;</hi> theſe cluſters doe hang vpon euerie hedge, and who then will thinke but the Sommer and Vintage is at hand? If we looke for fearefull ſignes from aboue, we haue ſeene the Sunne darkened and the Moone loſe her light, and the powers of Heauen ſhaken, and Starres falling from heauen, and prodigious Comets, which the ordinarie courſe of Nature could not produce. If we expect for ſignes from below, we haue heard the Seas roare, and the Earth make a noyſe, and the pillars of the Earth to tremble and quake. If we looke for the conuerſion of the Iewes, wee haue ſeene ſome branches of the naturall Vine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed againe into their ſtocke, and the ſonnes of <hi>Sem</hi> are daily collected into the Tents of their ancient Father. If the Goſpel muſt needes be preached in all the World, the ſound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3159:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath ſtretched vnto both the Pobes, and the gladſome tydings of Chriſt hath beene heard as farre as the courſe of the Sunne. If we looke for the appearing of Antichriſt, howſoeuer ſome doe dreame of one that ſhall ſpring from the Tribe of <hi>DAN,</hi> and of a Iew, yet cannot all the ſmoake which daily ariſeth out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit, obſcure the light of this truth, but that Antichriſt is alreadie reuealed, and daily aboliſhed by the brightneſſe of the Goſpel.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.</note> If we looke for the fulfilling of thoſe myſticall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies which were reuealed vnto <hi>Iohn,</hi> I thinke not title can be ſhewed which is vnaccompliſhed, but onely that ioyfull Epilogue of all Viſions,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ren.</hi> 20.12.</note> in the 20. Chapter, wherein a white Throne being placed in the Heauens, the Sonne of man iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both the quicke and the dead. Thus ſhall the Righteous ſtand with great boldneſſe before the face of ſuch as haue tormented them, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away their labours: Then ſhall the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſigh within themſelues, and ſay, Theſe are the men whom ſometimes we had in deriſion, and in a parable of reproch; We fooles thought their life madneſſe, and their end without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but now are they counted among the children of GOD, and their portion is amongſt the Saints. Then ſhall the wicked be couered with eternall confuſion, and the godly ſhall be crowned with euerlaſting glorie. Euen ſo, come <hi>LORD IESVS,</hi> and make an end of this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3159:34"/>wicked World, for thy Childrens ſake, that we may reigne with thee for euer; to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, glorie, power, praiſe, might, maieſtie, &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
